Hey y'all, Adam McFarland here from the
Sunno Music team and welcome back to our
channel. Today we're going to take a
look at some of the built-in effects
inside of Studio 2.0. Now, these effects
allow for you to uniquely dial in your
own sound and make these songs truly
your own. Maybe the coolest thing about
effects in Studio 2.0 is that you can
design your own plugins using the chat
bar. That's not something you can do in
most dolls. All right, y'all. Let's get
active. But first, let's take a listen
to a song that we were able to create
inside of Sununo Studio.
>> [music]
>> I love how clean and spacious this is
currently, but I do think that there's a
lot to offer in terms of adding effects
to this song. When you click add track
effects at the bottom of your screen,
the built-in plugins are going to pop up
here. Each plugin has a different way
that it affects the frequency and sound
of any individual track. We're going to
go in deeper detail about what each of
these plugins actually do in just a
minute. Before we go any further, let's
take a listen at the three main
components of this song. The synth, the
bass, and the drums. I'm going to solo
each one individually just so you can
hear how they sound without any effects
whatsoever. We call that dry.
[music]
Let's hear our bass. [music]
All right. And next, our drums. [music]
I'm going to add a different effect to
each line just so you could hear how
individual effects affect different
instruments. All right, let's start with
compression. [music]
>> Now, compression is essentially an
effect that helps to even out the volume
of a particular sound. It quiets the
loud parts and lifts the softer parts so
that everything feels a bit more
consistent and level. Let's add in some
compression to our baseline.
>> [music]
>> I'm going to make it a little cleaner.
[music]
All right.
The next effect we're going to focus on
is equalization, more commonly known as
EQ. You use EQ to adjust the balance of
different frequencies within a sound.
Those frequencies include the lows, the
mids, the highs. You use it to make
something brighter, to make something
warmer, or to clean up muddy or harsh
tones within a sound. All right, now
let's EQ one of our tracks inside of
this song. So, currently I have the
baseline soloed. Let's try and EQ our
synth chords. Let's hear how they sound
currently.
[music]
Let's add in a track effect by clicking
the add track effects button at the
bottom of our screen. And let's go to
EQ. As it is currently, the EQ line is
completely flat. But by offering the
different nodes within the EQ effect, I
can increase the high-end or decrease
the lowend. I'm going to kind of play
around with a couple of different
changes just so you can see the effects
that happen as a result of the different
movements within the EQ effect.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Let's add in some bottom again.
Maybe [music] let's take out some of the
highs here just to hear how it sounds.
>> [music]
>> So, where we landed here, I think I took
out some of the highs and kind of added
a little bit in the middle here to make
the sound a little bit almost muted.
[music] Next, let's talk about reverb
and convolution. Reverb is an effect
that adds a sense of space, like the
sound is playing inside of a real room,
inside of a concert hall, or inside of a
church. Convolution is a special type of
reverb. A type that uses an actual
recording of space called an impulse
response to make that sound sound more
authentic and real. Let's add some
reverb to our synth arpeggio. Take a
listen to how it sounds by itself.
Pretty cool sound, but let's hear how it
sounds with some reverb. Here we go.
Let's
take it up.
>> [music]
>> All right, let's go back to our piano
line and add in a little more
convolution here as well. Let's see how
it sounds whenever we play it at the
halls of the Pantheon.
[music]
[bell]
So much dissonance and I almost argue
too much. So, I'm going to pull down our
decay a little bit, increase the
dampening, and let's hear it inside of a
freight elevator. Here we go.
[music]
All right. It's a pretty cool sound.
Let's hear this inside of the mix.
>> [music]
>> here with our sis. They're kind of
bouncing off of each other inside the
track. [music]
[music] Right. So, we were able to add
in some reverb and some convolution to
our piano chords and our synth arpeggio
line. Now, I want to also be very clear
like these are decisions that I made.
Maybe you wouldn't make those decisions.
Maybe you do something different.
Completely fine. There's no right or
wrong way to do it. It's just about our
ability to tailor make and uniquely
create what sounds like us.
Next, let's talk about delay. Delay is
an effect that repeats a sound after a
short gap, creating an echo effect. You
can set how fast repeats come and how
quickly they fade, from a subtle
thickening to a rhythmic bouncing echo.
Let's add some delay to our baseline. I
already have some compressor and some
reverb on this baseline. So, I'm
actually going to take those off just so
we can hear what specifically delay
does. I can add in an effect by clicking
add effect and select delay. Let's hear
how the baseline sounds with just a
little bit of delay added.
[music]
Let's increase the time.
>> [music]
>> our time back down.
And let's add a little bit of feedback,
[music]
more rhythmic.
I'm going to go back to the top so you
can hear with the feedback turned up so
it turns a little bit more rhythmic in
its nature.
>> [music]
>> I personally like to use delay on
baselines sometimes to almost act as a
second form of percussion. [music]
Let's hear it in the mix.
[music]
>> [music]
>> set free tonight.
>> All right, not mad at that. Going to
leave it there. If I want to make any
changes, it's always there for me to
alter more. [music]
>> Lastly, we're going to talk about
distortion. Now, I like to say
distortion is grit. It adds an edge to a
sound. It pushes it beyond its clean
limits. It makes audio feel a bit warmer
or rougher or more aggressive. It can
take something from a slight crunch to
like a heavy fuzz or a roar. Often times
we use distortion on guitar or on vocals
or on drums to give it more attitude.
But we can also use it in a more subtle
way just to give something a bit more
presence on the mix. Let's add some
distortion to our synth chords line.
Now, previously we added some EQ
changes. Let's hear where we landed
there.
[music] Kind of warm.
What if we wanted to change this a
little bit and make it stand out a
little bit more?
I'm going to add in some distortion by
pressing the plus sign here and clicking
distortion. And let's hear how the
distortion affects this synth chord line
just in its default form. Already hear a
little bit of difference there.
gritty
started clipping a little bit there. So,
I can always change the mix by bringing
the audio down slightly.
[music]
All right, I took a little bit of that
drive off, but I did kind of like how
that drive made it a little bit more
aggressive. So, let's hear from the top
where the tones are a little bit warmer
how this distortion affects that.
[music]
Let's fold it in a little bit. [music]
>> [music]
>> So, it got a little harsh there on the
edges. That was when I folded it. But,
let's make it asymmetrical. Try one more
time. [music]
Wow, that really changed the sound.
[music]
All
>> [music]
[music]
>> right, let's hear this inside the mix
because I think it's going to stand out
a whole lot more. [music]
[music]
>> [music]
>> There's a solo [music] with the
distortion and solo without. See how
much difference that is? Like a
completely different instrument. That
brings us to the end of this video about
audio effects inside of Studio 2.0. Jump
in the comments. Let us know what audio
effects you're looking forward to seeing
next. But until next time, this is Adam
signing off.
>> [music]
>> Thank you all so much for joining.